Finding Aid of America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee Record Group SR.198
State Archives of North Carolina
America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee Record Group
1937 - 1989
SR.198
198
MARS ID 198
40.0 boxes (includes 3 reels of microfilm)
40.00 13.00 3.00
Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee
State Archives of North Carolina
Box Exhibit and Festival Correspondence
Box Celebrations File
Box Archaeological File
Box Commemorative Events File
Box Logo File
Box Elizabeth II
Box Assistant Director's Office County File
Box Correspondence File
Box Minutes File
Box American Quadricentennial Corporation
Box Publications File
Box Iconographic Collection
Reel Newspaper Clippings File
Access Restrictions
Available for research
Historical note
Between 1984 and 1987 North Carolina commemorated the four hundredth anniversary of the Roanoke Voyages. Supported by Sir Walter Raleigh with the assistance of Queen Elizabeth I, the first expedition was sent to explore the coastal and sound regions of what is now North Carolina. Subsequent voyages attempted to found a military colony on Roanoke Island and an ongoing civilian settlement. While these objectives were only partially realized (the settlement is remembered as the Lost Colony), the voyages led the way for England to establish permanent colonies in America in the following century.
Through a joint resolution, the General Assembly of 1955 laid the foundation for a three-year celebration of the historical events. A body known as America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Commission was established to initiate plans toward a commemoration on the scale of a national or world's fair exposition, or as deemed appropriate. Consisting of not less than twenty-five nor more than fifty members, appointees to the commission were to be chosen by the governor on the following merits: capacity to deal with problems involved in a celebration of national scope, and knowledge of and interest in early American history. The resolution stipulated, however, that the commission's non-resident membership not exceed twenty percent. The commission's ex officio members were to include North Carolina's entire delegation to Congress.
In 1973 the legislature repealed the resolution creating the anniversary commission and established America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee in its place. Charged with advising the secretary of the Department of Cultural Resources in planning and implementing the commemorations, the anniversary committee consisted of four ex officio members and ten gubernatorial appointees who served staggered terms. Their successors served terms of four years. Those serving ex officio included the secretary of the Department of Natural and Economic Resources, the mayor of Manteo on Roanoke Island, and chairmen of the Roanoke Island Historical Association and the Dare County Board of Commissioners. The governor was authorized to appoint a member of the committee to serve as chairman. In 1977 the designation of the secretary of the Department of Natural and Economic Resources was changed when that department was reorganized as the Department of Natural Resources and Community Development.
In 1978 the American Quadricentennial Corporation, a 501(c)3 nonprofit organization, was created to provide private support for programs planned and executed by America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee. To ensure coordination between the two bodies, the president of the corporation also functioned as the chairman of the anniversary committee.
The executive director and staff of America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee reported directly to the secretary of the Department of Cultural Resources. Staff operations, however, were affiliated directly with the department's Division of Archives and History. During the years of planning, the following major objectives were sought by the division and committee: to conduct and promote solid historical and archaeological studies of England's first attempt to colonize America; to encourage the preservation and public exhibition of historic sites and artifacts associated with the expeditions; to cooperate with other agencies and organizations in developing better facilities in coastal North Carolina in anticipation of the celebration and the anticipated tourism afterwards; and to promote the state's heritage and attractions.
These aims had notable results, including the following: publication of a series of pamphlets and monographs on the region's history; a scholarly symposium on Sir Walter Raleigh and publication of the papers presented; an archaeological search for the sites of English colonists and Indian villages on Roanoke Island; addition of a number of historical markers on Roanoke Island and in England; and an exhibit of sixteenth-century artifacts and manuscripts, "Raleigh and Roanoke," jointly produced by the British Library and the North Carolina Museum of History and shown in London, Raleigh, and New York. Additionally, ELIZABETH II--a replica of a sailing ship of the period--was built and docked at a new state historic site located in Shallowbag Bay, the harbor for the town of Manteo. The anniversary committee also supported or endorsed many other projects, including a British-American Folk Festival and a nationally televised epic drama entitled ROANOKE, which was aired as a three-part miniseries. Commemorations were scheduled to end on 18 August 1987, the four- hundredth birthday of Virginia Dare, the first child of English parents born and baptized in America.
REFERENCES: S.L., 1955, Resolution 43. S.L., 1973, c. 476, ss. 74-76. S.L., 1977, c. 771, s. 4. G.S. 143B-85 through 143B-86 [1983]. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee. AMERICA'S FOUR HUNDREDTH ANNIVERSARY COMMITTEE: FINAL REPORT, by John D. Neville. Raleigh, [1990]. Pp. 1-93. Department of Cultural Resources. [Budget]. Raleigh, 1979/80. ---. DEPARTMENT OF CULTURAL RESOURCES. Raleigh, 1984. P. 17. Poff, Jan-Michael, ed. ADDRESSES AND PUBLIC PAPERS OF JAMES BAXTER HUNT, JR., GOVERNOR OF NORTH CAROLINA, VOLUME II, 1981-1985. Raleigh: Division of Archives and History, Department of Cultural Resources, 1987. Pp. 38, 316-317, 412-413, 479-480, 503-504. Powell, William S. NORTH CAROLINA THROUGH FOUR CENTURIES. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1989. Pp. 15-17, 33-50, 543-544.
Dept. of Cultural Resources (MARS # 57)
Raleigh, Walter, 1552?-1618
America's 400th Anniversary Committee; North Carolina. Department of Cultural Resources; American Quadricentennial Corporation; American Quadricentennial Corporation.; North Carolina. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee.; North Carolina. Department of Cultural Resources.; British Library.; North Carolina Museum of History.; United States. National Park Service.; Elizabeth II (Ship).
Centennial Celebrations; Exhibitions; Algonquian Indians; Archaeology; Underwater archaeology; Government publicity; Automobile license plates; Commemorative coins; Commemorative postage stamps; Medals; Visits of state; License agreements; Trademarks; Historic sites; Museum exhibits
Roanoke Island; Dare County (N.C.); Roanoke Colony; Dare County (N.C.); Roanoke Colony; Roanoke Island (N.C.); United States--Centennial celebrations, etc.; Elizabethan Gardens (Roanoke Island, N.C.); Fort Raleigh (N.C.); Fort Raleigh National Historic Site (N.C.); Roanoke Island Festival Park (N.C.); Great Britain
- Exhibit and Festival Correspondence, 1978-1987; SR.198.1; 1327; 198.1; Correspondence; 2.00; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources
  Arrangement
  Processed
  Cultural Resources, Dept. of
  Acquisitions Information
  Transferred from the agency to the State Records Center, 21 April 1988. Transferred from the SRC to the State Archives, 29 March 2007.
  Scope and Contents note
  General correspondence, commemorative souvenir information, committee and subcommittee correspondence, research reports, programs, brochures, Sir Francis Drake Conference memorabilia, photographs, and resolutions pertaining to planning and development of America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (AFHAC). Includes the files of H. G. Jones, first chairman of AFHA and first president of American Quadricentennial Corporation (AQC), which were transferred on 14 February 2005 from Chapel Hill, North Carolina to the State Archives and later merged into this series. Also, includes the rough draft materials and final official report of completed by John Neville on 15 May 1989.
  Schedule Reference
  RS No. 1327
  - Archaeology, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Archaeology)
  - Background for Commemoration, 1979-1980; SR.198.1.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Background for Commemoration)
  - British Embassy, 1982-1984; SR.198.1.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder British Embassy)
  - British Guest, 11-19 July 1984; SR.198.1.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder British Guest)
  - Budget, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Budget)
  - Commemorative Souvenirs: Coins, 1979-1986, undated; SR.198.1.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Commemorative Souvenirs: Coins)
  - Commemorative Souvenirs: Offers, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Commemorative Souvenirs: Offers)
  - Commemorative Souvenirs: Stamps: British Philatelic Bureau, 1972-1973, 1980, 1982-1983; SR.198.1.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Commemorative Souvenirs: Stamps: British Philatelic Bureau)
  - Commemorative Souvenirs: Stamps: Stamp meter logo, 1981, 1983-1984; SR.198.1.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Commemorative Souvenirs: Stamps: Stamp meter logo)
  - Commemorative Souvenirs: Stamps: United States Stamps, 1980-1986; SR.198.1.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Commemorative Souvenirs: Stamps: United States Stamps)
  - Committee Correspondence: Commemorative Events SubCommittee, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.002; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Commemorative Events SubCommittee)
  - Committee Correspondence: Committee Appointments, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.002; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Committee Appointments)
  - Committee Correspondence: Dare County Liaison SubCommittee, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.002; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Dare County Liaison SubCommittee)
  - Committee Correspondence: Education SubCommittee, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.002; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Education SubCommittee)
  - Committee Correspondence: Elizabeth II (Ship) SubCommittee: News clippings, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.002; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Elizabeth II (Ship) SubCommittee: News clippings)
  - Committee Correspondence: Elizabeth II (Ship) SubCommittee: SubCommittee Correspondence, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.002; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Elizabeth II (Ship) SubCommittee: SubCommittee Correspondence)
  - Committee Correspondence: General Correspondence, 1982-1984; SR.198.1.002; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: General Correspondence)
  - Committee Correspondence: Jones, H. G. (Chairman of AFHAC): General Correspondence, 1977-1984; SR.198.1.002; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Jones, H. G. (Chairman of AFHAC): General Correspondence,)
  - Committee Correspondence: Jones, H. G. (Chairman of AFHAC): Quinn, David Beers, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Jones, H. G. (Chairman of AFHAC): Quinn, David Beers)
  - Committee Correspondence: Jones, H. G. (Chairman of AFHAC): Wallis, Helen, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Jones, H. G. (Chairman of AFHAC): Wallis, Helen)
  - Committee Correspondence: Music Advisory Committee, 1983-1984, undated; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Music Advisory Committee)
  - Committee Correspondence: North Carolina Humanities Committee, 1976, 1980-1986, undated; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: North Carolina Humanities Committee)
  - Committee Correspondence: Neville, John, 1981, 1986-1987; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Neville, John)
  - Committee Correspondence: Publications SubCommittee, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Publications SubCommittee)
  - Committee Correspondence: Regional Liaison SubCommittee, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Regional Liaison SubCommittee)
  - Committee Correspondence: Special Activities SubCommittee, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Committee Correspondence: Special Activities SubCommittee)
  - Cronkite, Walter, 1983-1984; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Cronkite, Walter)
  - Elizabethan Festival (13-14 July 1984), Working File of Historically Speaking, 1984, undated; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Elizabethan Festival (13-14 July 1984), Working File of Historically Speaking)
  - Elizabethan Festival (13-14 July 1985), Touring Program Grant Evaluation Form, 21 June 1985; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Elizabethan Festival (13-14 July 1985), Touring Program Grant Evaluation Form)
  - Elizabethan Gardens Reception, 1983-1984, 1987, undated; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Elizabethan Gardens Reception)
  - Exhibit Development Meetings (Roanoke Island Voyages, 1584-1587), October 1983; SR.198.1.003; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Exhibit Development Meetings (Roanoke Island Voyages, 1584-1587))
  - Film Production, "Roanoak," (Dry Salvage Film Group), undated; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Film Production, "Roanoak," (Dry Salvage Film Group))
  - Film Project, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Film Project,)
  - Flotilla Events, 1983-1984, undated; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Flotilla Events)
  - Houston-Fearing Project, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Houston-Fearing Project)
  - License Plate, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder License Plate)
  - "Lost Colony" Drama, 1981-1984, 1987, undated; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder "Lost Colony" Drama)
  - Manteo Revitalization, 1978-1980; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Manteo Revitalization)
  - Meetings (Chairman's Records), 5 August 1978; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Meetings (Chairman's Records))
  - Meetings (Chairman's Records), 14 November 1978; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Meetings (Chairman's Records))
  - Meetings (Chairman's Records), 17-18 August 1979; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Meetings (Chairman's Records))
  - Meetings (Chairman's Records), 6 November 1979; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Meetings (Chairman's Records))
  - Meetings (Chairman's Records), 29 February-March 1, 1980; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Meetings (Chairman's Records))
  - Meetings (Chairman's Records), 27-28 June 1980; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Meetings (Chairman's Records))
  - Meetings (Chairman's Records), 19-20 September 1980; SR.198.1.004; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Meetings (Chairman's Records))
  - Membership, 1977-1980, undated; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Membership)
  - Memorabilia from Sir Francis Drake Conference, California, 1979; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Memorabilia from Sir Francis Drake Conference, California)
  - Memorandums (1984 events), 1982-1984; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Memorandums (1984 events))
  - Photographs: Elizabeth II Keel, undated; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Photographs: Elizabeth II Keel)
  - Photographs: Neville, John (executive director), undated; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Photographs: Neville, John (executive director))
  - Photographs: Pomeiooc Indian Village Excavation, undated; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Photographs: Pomeiooc Indian Village Excavation)
  - Photographs: Signal Fire Commemoration, undated; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Photographs: Signal Fire Commemoration)
  - Photographs: St. Stephens Baptist Church Parade Float (Spring Hope Pumpkin Festival), undated; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Photographs: St. Stephens Baptist Church Parade Float (Spring Hope Pumpkin Festival))
  - Photographs: Tree Planting Ceremony (Raleigh, NC), 7 October 1984; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Photographs: Tree Planting Ceremony (Raleigh, NC))
  - Plaque for Manteo, 1984, undated; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Plaque for Manteo)
  - Reports: Final Report of AFHAC: Rough Draft Materials, undated; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Reports: Final Report of AFHAC: Rough Draft Materials)
  - Reports: Final Report of AFHAC: Final Draft, 1989; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Reports: Final Report of AFHAC: Final Draft)
  - Reports: Garret, George, "Living with Elizabethans", 1985; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Reports: Garret, George, "Living with Elizabethans")
  - Reports: General Assembly, February 1985; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Reports: General Assembly)
  - Reports: Kupperman, Dr. Karen, "English Colonists Confront the American Environment", undated; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder Reports: Kupperman, Dr. Karen, "English Colonists Confront the American Environment")
  - US Senate Joint Resolutions, 7-10 March 1983; SR.198.1.005; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder US Senate Joint Resolutions)
- Celebrations File, 1980-1987; SR.198.2; 198.2; 3690; Correspondence; 1.00; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources
  Transferred from the agency to the State Records Center, 24 October 1986 and 21 April 1988. Transferred from the SRC to the State Archives, 19 February 1993 and 29 March 2007.
  Correspondences, memorandums, pamphlets, brochures, newsletters, grant applications, and programs covering various celebrations held in honor of the anniversary. Series includes British American Festival, British Library Exhibition, Commission of Indian Affairs, Elizabethan Gardens and Rendezvous Festival, English Speaking Union, and Roanoke Island Historical Association materials.
  RS No. 3690
  - British American Festival (Duke University, 2-16 June 1984): Correspondence, 1981-1984, undated; SR.198.2.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder British American Festival (Duke University, 2-16 June 1984): Correspondence)
  - British Library Exhibition (NC Museum of History): Correspondence, 1980-1984, undated; SR.198.2.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder British Library Exhibition (NC Museum of History): Correspondence)
  - British Library Exhibition (NC Museum of History): Memorandums, 1981-1985, undated; SR.198.2.001; Department of Natural and Cultural Resources. America's Four Hundredth Anniversary Committee (Folder British Library Exhibition (NC Museum of History): Memorandums)